<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<elements>
    <info>
        <name></name>
        <update version="0.0.1">
            <file name="bard-skald.xml" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/ShadowLinks/northlands-elements/refs/heads/main/bard-skald.xml" />
        </update>
    </info>
    <element name="Skald" type="Archetype" source="Northlands (2024)"  id="ID_KPB_NL_ARCHETYPE_BARD_SKALD">
        <supports>Bard Subclass</supports>
        <description>
            <p class="flavor">Provoke, Manipulate, Inspire</p>
            <p>Northlands Bards have passed down skaldic traditions through the ages at their bardic colleges. They use these traditions to entertain in the feasthalls during the long, dark winters; to lift up great leaders and to tear down despots; and to direct the tempers of their Northern kin in productive directions. Skalds are battle-trained to travel with warrior-bands and adventuring groups. Their skills with weapons and words keep them safe while they write the stories of their exploits, sing drinking songs in mead halls, and recite poems of legendary heroes on raider longships.</p>
            <div element="ID_KP_NL_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_BARD_SKALD_POETIC_PROVOCATION" />
            <div element="ID_KP_NL_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_BARD_SKALD_MARTIAL_TRAINING" />
            <div element="ID_KP_NL_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_BARD_SKALD_BRAGIS_RUNE_OF_SPEECH" />
            <div element="ID_KP_NL_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_BARD_SKALD_BATTLE_SAGAS" />
        </description>
        <sheet display="false">
            <description></description>
        </sheet>
        <rules>
            <grant type="Archetype Feature" id="ID_KP_NL_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_BARD_SKALD_POETIC_PROVOCATION" level="3" />
            <grant type="Archetype Feature" id="ID_KP_NL_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_BARD_SKALD_MARTIAL_TRAINING" level="3" />
            <grant type="Archetype Feature" id="ID_KP_NL_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_BARD_SKALD_BRAGIS_RUNE_OF_SPEECH" level="6" />
            <grant type="Archetype Feature" id="ID_KP_NL_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_BARD_SKALD_BATTLE_SAGAS" level="14" />

        </rules>
    </element>
    <element name="Level 3: Poetic Provocation" type="Archetype Feature" source="Northlands (2024)"  id="ID_KP_NL_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_BARD_SKALD_POETIC_PROVOCATION">
        <requirements>!ID_INTERNAL_KP_NL_FEATURE_REPLACEMENT_BARBARIAN_POETIC_PROVOCATION</requirements>
        <description>
            <p>Thanks to your way with words, you gain the following benefits.</p>
            <p class="indent"><strong>Vicious Cantrip.</strong> You always have the Vicious Mockery cantrip prepared. If you already know the Vicious Mockery cantrip, you learn a new cantrip of your choice. A creature that fails its saving throw against your Vicious Mockery has Disadvantage on the next Wisdom, Intelligence, or Charisma saving throw that it makes before the end of your next turn, in addition to the spell’s normal effects.</p>
            <p class="indent"><strong>Flyting Master.</strong> You can use Charisma (Performance) in place of Charisma (Intimidation) or Charisma (Persuasion) checks to antagonize a creature into a fight, threaten a creature to avoid a confrontation, rile or soothe the attitude of a mob, or any other situation where your skill in weaving a story or applying a cutting insult would sway an opinion.</p>
        </description>
        <sheet alt="Poetic Provocation">
            <description>Vicious Cantrip: A creature that fails its saving throw against your Vicious Mockery has Disadvantage on the next WIS, INT, or CHA saving throw that it makes before the end of your next turn, in addition to the spell’s normal effects.
            Flyting Master: You can use Charisma (Performance) in place of Charisma (Intimidation) or Charisma (Persuasion) checks to antagonize a creature into a fight, threaten a creature to avoid a confrontation, rile or soothe the attitude of a mob, or any other situation where your skill in weaving a story or applying a cutting insult would sway an opinion.</description>
        </sheet>
        <rules>
            <select type="Spell" name="Poetic Provocation" supports="Bard,0" spellcasting="Bard" default="ID_WOTC_PHB24_SPELL_VICIOUS_MOCKERY" default-behaviour="force" />
        </rules>
    </element>
    <element name="Level 6: Martial Training" type="Archetype Feature" source="Northlands (2024)"  id="ID_KP_NL_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_BARD_SKALD_MARTIAL_TRAINING">
        <requirements>!ID_INTERNAL_KP_NL_FEATURE_REPLACEMENT_BARD_SKALD_MARTIAL_TRAINING</requirements>
        <description>
            <p>You gain proficiency with Martial weapons and training with Medium armor and Shields. In addition, you can use a Simple or Martial weapon as a Spellcasting Focus to cast spells from the Bard spell list.</p>
            <p class="indent">In addition, your training with weapons allows you to use the mastery properties of one Simple or Martial weapon of your choice. Whenever you finish a Long Rest, you can practice weapon drills and change your weapon choice.</p>
        </description>
        <sheet alt="Martial Training">
            <description>You can use a Simple or Martial weapon as a Spellcasting Focus to cast spells from the Bard spell list.
            In addition, you can usethe mastery properites of one Simple or Martial weapon of your choice and can practice with a weapon during a long rest to change it.</description>
        </sheet>
        <rules>
            <grant type="Proficiency" id="ID_PROFICIENCY_WEAPON_PROFICIENCY_MARTIAL_WEAPONS" />
            <grant type="Proficiency" id="ID_PROFICIENCY_ARMOR_PROFICIENCY_MEDIUM_ARMOR" />
            <grant type="Proficiency" id="ID_PROFICIENCY_ARMOR_PROFICIENCY_SHIELDS" />
            <select type="Class Feature" name="Weapon Mastery (Martial Training)" supports="Weapon Mastery" number="1"/>
        </rules>
    </element>
    <element name="Level 10: Bragi's Rune of Speech" type="Archetype Feature" source="Northlands (2024)"  id="ID_KP_NL_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_BARD_SKALD_BRAGIS_RUNE_OF_SPEECH">
        <requirements>!ID_INTERNAL_KP_NL_FEATURE_REPLACEMENT_BARD_SKALD_BRAGIS_RUNE_OF_SPEECH</requirements>
        <description>
            <p>As a Bonus Action, you may expend a use of Bardic Inspiration to cause one of the following effects:</p>
            <p class="indent"><strong>Scorn. </strong>Choose one creature within 30 feet to make a Wisdom saving throw. On a failed save, the target has Disadvantage on its attack rolls against you for 1 minute.</p>
            <p class="indent"><strong>Eloquence. </strong>You may roll your Bardic Inspiration die and add the result to the first Charisma check or saving throw you make in the next hour.</p>
            <p class="indent"><strong>Vitality. </strong>You may roll your Bardic Inspiration die. You and up to three allies within 30 feet gain Temporary Hit Points equal to the result of the roll.</p>
            <p class="indent">You may have only one of these effects active at a time. If you use another, it replaces the one that is currently active.</p>
        </description>
        <sheet alt="Bragi's Rune of Speech" action="Bonus Action">
            <description>As a Bonus Action, you may expend a use of Bardic Inspiration to cause one of the following effects:
            Scorn. Choose one creature within 30 feet to make a WIS saving throw. On a failed save, the target has Disadvantage on its attack rolls against you for 1 minute.
            Eloquence. You may roll your Bardic Inspiration die and add the result to the first CHA check or saving throw you make in the next hour.
            Vitality. You may roll your Bardic Inspiration die. You and up to three allies within 30 feet gain the roll as Temporary Hit Points.
            You may have only one of these effects active at a time. If you use another, it replaces the one that is currently active.</description>
        </sheet>
    </element>
    <element name="Level 14: Battle Sagas" type="Archetype Feature" source="Northlands (2024)"  id="ID_KP_NL_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_BARD_SKALD_BATTLE_SAGAS">
        <requirements>!ID_INTERNAL_KP_NL_FEATURE_REPLACEMENT_BARD_SKALD_BATTLE_SAGAS</requirements>
        <description>
            <p>You have learned to channel the power from the Eddas, epic poems of heroes, monsters, and gods ingrained into the hearts and minds of the Northlanders. You can spend 1 minute reciting selected passages from the Eddas. When you do so, each creature your choice (other than you) within 60 feet, that can hear you, gains several benefits for 1 hour.</p>
            <ul>
                <li>It has Resistance to Poison damage and Immunity to the Frightened and Poisoned conditions.</li>
                <li>Its Hit Point maximum increases by 2d10, and it gains the same number of Hit Points</li>
                <li>Once per turn, when the creature makes an attack roll or saving throw, it can add 1d4 to the roll or save.</li>
            </ul>
        </description>
        <sheet alt="Battle Sagas">
            <description>You can spend 1 minute reciting selected passages from the Eddas. When you do so, each creature your choice (other than you) within 60 feet, that can hear you, gains several benefits for 1 hour.
            - It has Resistance to Poison damage and Immunity to the Frightened and Poisoned conditions.
            - Its Hit Point maximum increases by 2d10, and it gains the same number of Hit Points
            - Once per turn, when the creature makes an attack roll or saving throw, it can add 1d4 to the roll or save.</description>
        </sheet>
    </element>
    
    <element name="Poetic Provocation Feature Replacement" type="Grants" source="Internal" id="ID_INTERNAL_KP_NL_FEATURE_REPLACEMENT_BARBARIAN_POETIC_PROVOCATION"/>
    <element name="Martial Training Feature Replacement" type="Grants" source="Internal" id="ID_INTERNAL_KP_NL_FEATURE_REPLACEMENT_BARD_SKALD_MARTIAL_TRAINING"/>
    <element name="Bragi's Rune of Speech Feature Replacement" type="Grants" source="Internal" id="ID_INTERNAL_KP_NL_FEATURE_REPLACEMENT_BARD_SKALD_BRAGIS_RUNE_OF_SPEECH"/>
    <element name="Battle Sagas Feature Replacement" type="Grants" source="Internal" id="ID_INTERNAL_KP_NL_FEATURE_REPLACEMENT_BARD_SKALD_BATTLE_SAGAS"/>
</elements>